Taylor A. Howell

OPTIMIZATION · CONTROL · ROBOTICS

Durand 032, Stanford, CA 94305 USA



Summary_

Currently, I am a Ph.D. candidate at Stanford University. I work on optimization-based tools for motion planning of complex, underactuated robotic systems. My expertise include: numerical optimization, technical computing, automatic control, and modeling of dynamical systems.

Education_

Stanford University

Stanford, CA, USA

Ph.D. in Mechanical Engineering Sept. 2017 - June. 2022 (expected)

• Automatic Controls, Robotics

· Advisors: Zachary Manchester, Allison Okamura

Stanford University

Stanford, CA, USA

M.S. IN MECHANICAL ENGINEERING

Sept. 2017 - June. 2019

• Automatic Controls, Robotics

Salt Lake City, UT, USA

University of Utah

B.S. IN MECHANICAL ENGINEERING

Summa Cum Laude

May 2013 - Dec. 2016

• Capstone Project: Wireless Power for Aerial Robots

Research_

Robotic Exploration Lab, Stanford University

Stanford, CA, USA

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

May 2018 - present

My research is focused on developing optimization-based tools for motion planning of underactuated robotic systems. Currently, I am working on algorithms for robust feedback motion planning and solvers for contact-implicit trajectory optimization. Previously, I was co-leading development of TrajectoryOptimization.jl, an open-source Julia package for solving constrained trajectory optimization problems.

Telerobotics Laboratory, University of Utah

Salt Lake City, UT, USA

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Oct. 2015 - Dec. 2016

I devised and implemented a control scheme to sort swarms of microrobots using rotating uniform magnetic fields for minimally invasive medical applications. This work included: applied physics, simulation, nonlinear optimization, fabrication of a scaled microrobot swarm, and writing C++ code to control a tri-axial Helmholtz-coil system.

Utah Center of Excellence for Biomedical Microfluidics, University of Utah

Salt Lake City, UT, USA

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Sept. 2014 - Oct. 2015

I designed and built a forty-eight-syringe pump for a medical microfluidic system, developed standard operating procedures for a high-throughput drug screening and cytotoxicity evaluation system, and performed statistical analysis for ovarian-cancer cell experiments.

JUNE 3, 2021

TAYLOR A. HOWELL . CURRICULUM VITAE

Publications

Linearized Contact-Implicit Model-Predictive Control, S. Le Cleac'h*, T. Howell*, M. Schwager, Z. 2021

Manchester. (prepared).

Direct Policy Optimization using Deterministic Sampling and Collocation, T. Howell, C. Fu, Z. Manchester.

Robotics and Automation Letters.

Scalable Cooperative Transport of Cable-Suspended Loads with UAVs using Distributed Trajectory

2020 Optimization, B. Jackson*, T. Howell*, K. Shah, M. Schwager, Z. Manchester. Robotics and Automation

ALTRO: A Fast Solver for Constrained Trajectory Optimization, T. Howell*, B. Jackson*, Z. Manchester. 2019 International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems. Macao, China.

Sorting Rotating Micromachines By Variations in Their Magnetic Properties, T. Howell, B. Osting, J. 2018 Abbott. Physical Review Applied.

Use of a highly parallel Microfluidic Flow Cell Array to determine therapeutic drug dose response 2017 curves, J. Arellano, T. Howell, J. Gammon, S. Cho, M. Janat Amsbury, B. Gale. Biomedical Microdevices.

Skills

Programming Julia, C++, Python, Matlab, R

Computational كتابك, Git, Linux, SNOPT, Ipopt, Convex.jl, MeshCat, Solidworks, ROS, Adobe Premiere Pro, Adobe Illustrator, Arduino

Fabrication Mill, Lathe, Vacuum Forming, Laser Cutting, Mold Making and Casting, Metal Sheet Fabrication

Experience _____

Google San Francisco, CA, USA (remote)

June. 2021 - Sept. 2021 RESEARCH INTERN

Stanford, CA, USA

Apr. 2021 - Jun. 2021

Salt Lake City, UT, USA

Jun. 2017 - Jul. 2017

Apr. 2013 - Aug. 2013

Aug. 2007 - Jan. 2011

· differential physics, model-predictive control, manipulation

Department of Aeronautics and Astronautics, Stanford University

COURSE ASSISTANT - DYNAMICS AND CONTROL OF AIRCRAFT (AA271A)

· held office hours four times per week

· graded assignments and exams

Department of Computer Science, University of Utah

INSTRUCTOR - GREAT SUMMER CAMP

· led a teaching team of three

- · taught practical robotics and programming skills to elementary school students using the LEGO Mindstorm platform
- developed projects and challenges for FLL skills, telerobotics, and kinetic-art themed weeks

Cornaby-Howell LLC Salt Lake City, UT, USA

CO-FOUNDER, ENGINEER

FRONT DESK CLERK

TWISTY PUZZLES

Apr. 2015 - Oct. 2015

- · prototyped systems: touch-display module with GUI, Arduino C code, a lead-screw system, and syringe attachment modules for precision high-throughput syringe pumps
- · designed hardware schematics for patent application

Ramada Limited Draper Draper, UT, USA

· manager on duty: checked in and out guests, made reservations, and ran breakfast

developed communication and practical problem solving skills

Designer Draper, UT, USA

designed and built twisty puzzles with selling prices ranging from \$25 - \$850

exhibited my work at the community's premier international event: Dutch Cube Day 2008

Community Outreach _____

JUNE 3, 2021 TAYLOR A. HOWELL · CURRICULUM VITAE

- 2019 **Co-organizer**, of Social Impact Night event at Stanford University to connect social-impact focused students and entrepreneurs
- **Mentor**, to three summer interns at the Telerobotics Laboratory and developed soft robots with potential as catheter tips that will increase insertion distance deep in the brain and other hard-to-reach locations in the
- 2015 Science-fair Judge, for local elementary school to provide feedback to students about their projects

Fellowships & Scholarships_

Stanford Graduate Fellowship (2017 – 2018) · University of Utah Undergraduate Research Opportunities Program Fellowship (2016) · The Boeing Company Scholarship (2016) · Shirley L. & Kathelyne O. Evans Endowed Scholarship (2016) · Big Ten+ Grad Expo Travel Scholarship (2016) · University of Utah Presidential Scholarship (2013 – 2016)

Coursework.

Convex Optimization · Optimal Control · Nonlinear Control · Advanced Software Development · Engineering Design Optimization · Deep Learning · State Estimation · Principles of Robotic Autonomy · Introduction to Mechatronics · Linear Dynamical Systems · Introduction to Robotics · Machine Learning · Decision Making Under Uncertainty · Control Design Techniques · Advanced Robotic Manipulation · Advanced Feedback Control · Introduction to Optimization · Experimental Robotics · Multi-robot Systems · State Space Control · Design of Experiments · Introduction to Finite Element Method · Programming for Engineers · RL for Stochastic Control in Finance